...And them as were still alive, where'd they go?
人既然还活着 那么他们会去哪儿
Every which way, like ghosts, on the fields...
形似幽灵 浪迹田野
By October, the town was deserted.
一到十月 小镇如同废城
All you heard was: "Step aside, it's the undertakers!"
你只听得见 闪一边去 收尸的来了
They piled them together, dead and plagued.
不管死的还是中瘟的 全都堆一起
They tried to gather them from every corner of town
他们把小镇人们从角角落落聚在一起
but the dead stayed in the streets'til the undertakers came.
但死掉的只能被扔在路边等人收尸
Then they buried them in gardens.
然后全都埋进花园
And the fearsome death kept on 'til January.
直到一月大家都还被死亡梦魇所缠绕
- Poor souls...  - Great woe for the Christians!
- 可怜啊…  - 天主教徒的悲哀啊
- There was also thieves dressed as undertakers.  - How so?
- 有的贼还会扮成收尸的  - 怎么会这样
With a red scarf 'round their necks.
他们脖上绕条红围巾作标志
They went around thieving, taking money, silverware...
四处到处抢钱偷物
People fled them like death
人们把他们当成瘟神驱赶
for they picked up the ill, too
因为他们连病人都抢
threw them into the wagon and hit them with a bat over the head.
人们将其丢进马车 然后乱棍打死
But worse still were the living abandoned
但是最惨的是那些活着就被遗弃的人
with no cover on the frozen fields.
赤身裸体就被丢入冰天雪地
All around you heard the screams
荒野随处可听
of the miserable souls in the fields at Dudesti...
那身世悲惨的幽灵的哀鸣
Ah, Christ's blood!
我的老天爷啊
And we, the living,
而我们这些活着的人
thought ourselves dead and wandered around, dazed.
也将自己视为行尸走肉 空有皮囊
WALLACHIA, 1835
瓦拉几亚 一八三五年
Look, Satan's coming!
撒旦来了
Oi, aunt, wait!
阿伯 等等
Good day to you, constable.
你好 警察大人
As good as your soul! Are you scared?
跟你一样好 你怕我吗
No.
不怕
Good, the clear sky fears not the lightning.
很好 身正不怕雷劈
- Who are you?  - A good soul.
- 你是谁  - 一个好人
We'll see 'bout that.
再说吧
Whence are you coming?
你哪儿来的
I'm of Geanache's, Leana by name...
我是吉纳契家的人…
I think I know you.
我应该认识你
Where are you going, you hag?
你上哪儿去
Taking my ol' man to kiss the Virgin's icon.
带我老爸去亲圣母像
He is dying and will leave me alone.
他要离开我 就快死了
- What ails him?  - The fever.
- 他怎么了  - 发烧了
Go away! It could be the cholera! You'll kill us.
挪开 搞不好是霍乱 你会害死我们的
You didn't ask.
你又没事先问我
You should have told us yourself, stupid cow!
你应该自己主动跟我们讲啊 蠢货
I ought to give your fat ass a whipping...
我应该好好打你一顿才是…
Fuck you, crone!
滚鸡巴蛋
Did you cross the forest?
你刚有穿过树林吗
Nay, I was afraid.
没 我怕
Are the Gypsy gold panners still in the forest?
那群吉普赛的淘金队在林子里吗
I don't know.
我不知道
Where are you taking your man?
你要带你爸去哪儿
I hope to find a nun to give him some herbs...
我想着找个修女 给他点草药…
She'll give him some bell juice, priest's song...
她只会给他喝果汁 再给他唱圣歌…
...and some spade oil.
然后叫你去挖个坟
Out of my sight!
滚你妈的
Filthy plague rat...
瘟神…
Barefoot hag...
连鞋都不穿…
We have business with the abbot.
我们要找院长
What business?
有何贵干
A secret from boyar Candescu.
坎德斯古公爵的私事
Father Superior!
神父
The poor prays more than the rich
穷人祷告总比富人还勤快
because he has time.
因为他们有时间
Lord be with us!
上帝与我们同在
Good day, bright lord.
你好 先生
The constable is here for some enquiries.
警察大人有事造访
If you know anything, speak up.
要是你知道些什么 就说出来
How many souls here?
这儿有多少人
Thirty souls. Ten died...
十个死的 三十个活的
Who's Carfin's sister?
谁是卡芬妹妹
Me, bright lord.
我
- 他在哪里  - 我不知道
crow指代吉普赛人 后文根据句意做了适当翻译
Haven't seen him since I was sold to the monastery here...
我被卖进修道院后就再没见过他
- You don't know, eh?!  - I don't!
- 不知道是吗  - 不知道
Tell him!
告诉他
Stay out of it, that's my craft.
别碰它 那是我做的
Crow, what's your name?
你叫什么名字
Pena.
潘纳
Want to taste this whip?
你不会想挨打吧
Sure I don't.
当然不想
Where is he, filthy whore?
他在哪儿 贱货
Tell me, or I'll whip all you slaves to death!
说不说 不然我就就把你们这帮奴隶抽死
Where is he?
他在哪儿
We don't know nothing, sir.
我们什么都不知道
I'll give you a silver coin.
说了我就给你们银币
We don't know.
我们都不知道
The monks beats us all the time, but we don't know.
僧侣们老打我们 但我们真的不知道
Say what?
你说什么
Said we don't know!
我说我们不知道
He went to the gold panners.
他去找淘金人了
How do you know?
你怎么知道
He told me when we were sowing.
我们种地的时候他自个儿说的
Said there's more freedom there.
他说那儿比较自由
Fine.
好
Merciful lord, the coin!
大人 那说好的钱呢
Fuck off, crows! You'll get the coin when I find him.
滚你妈蛋 找到人再说
Back to work, crows!
都回去工作 吉普赛佬
Gypsies, can't change them...
吉普赛人就这副德性…
Don't we know it?!
你以为我不知道吗
Our own good brandy.
来尝尝我们的上好白兰地
Enjoy it.
好好享用
Worthy of the Wedding at Cana!
婚礼用的上等货
Our thanks, Father.
谢谢你 神父
God be with you.
上帝与你们同在
How 'bout a riddle?
猜个谜语如何
Let's hear it.
说来听听
Lifeless out of life
什么无生命源自于生命
life out of lifeless.
什么生命源自于无生命
Doomsday...
末日审判到了…
No.You say it, Ionita.
你说答案吧 欧尼塔
The egg,for the hen lays it lifeless,
鸡蛋 刚出来时毫无生机
and when it hatches,it comes to life.
孵化后又充满生机的
The chicken!
是鸡
Go with the Lord.
大神们慢走
I'm getting lame...
我有点脚疼
Father, I'm cold.
父亲 我冷
If you caught that fever, you're fucked.
要是你真发烧了 那你就死定了
Cholera morbus,as the big doctors say...
霍乱不分贫贵 医生都是这么说的
You're such a waste of bread!
你就是个窝囊废
How's he going to be an officer?
怎样才能当警察
If you slap him, he'll die of grief.
赏他一巴掌就够他死心了
Ain't that you?
你就这样吧
No, t'aint.
不是我
Watch your mouth.
说话小心点
Honour thy mother and father,as the Gospel says,
福音书上有说 要尊敬长辈
for a father weighs more than twelve children...
一个父亲抵得过一打孩子
Sure I honour you.
我当然很尊敬您
Stab the enemy like a man!
像个真爷们杀敌
This is a sword from Ianina,show some respect!
这把剑产自约阿尼纳 让我看看
Not bad, the priest's brandy! Cures any sickness.
这白兰地不赖嘛 喝完包治百病
- Try some.- Don't want to.
- 喝点  - 我不想喝
Drink like a man!
像个男人 喝了它
You don't taste good brandy,you down it.
好酒不抿 大口来
Crush those Russians!
打倒那些俄罗斯人
Look at all those lazy crows.
看看这些懒散的吉普赛佬
Where are you going?
你要去哪
Get him, Ionita!
欧尼塔 抓住他
Stop or I shoot!
别动 不然我就开枪
Carfin, you fucking bastard!
卡芬 你个混账王八蛋
I didn't steal nothing, bright lord.
我没偷东西
Back off, crows!
退后 你们这帮吉普赛佬
He didn't do nothin'! Don't kill him!
他没做什么 别杀他
Spare him his life!
饶他一命
Stay out, or I'll kill you too!
别过来 否则我连你也杀
Is he from your camp?
他是你们的人吗
He's our Caldasin.
他是我们的卡达辛
Why'd you run?
那你干嘛跑
For fear, bright lord.
我怕啊 大人
Can you read?
你识字吗
I can't.
不会
Here!
拿着
Don't drop it.
别掉了
"...to you, lawkeeper Costandin sin Gheorghe,
致康斯坦丁执法官…
this letter gives all power
我将授予一切权力…
to catch the Gypsy slave Carfin Pandoleon:
缉拿吉普赛奴隶卡芬
tall of stature, dark of face,
此人人高马大 面色黝黑
who also speaks the Gypsy language.
操一口吉普赛语
This Gypsy fled from boyar Iordache Candescu
此人背弃主人坎德斯古公爵
and stole money from a box.
并窃取了公爵钱箱
Should you not bring said slave,
任何人要是知情不报
we shall put you in chains
也将会被关进大牢
and bring upon you great punishment.These we write..."
并予严厉惩治 以上…
Enough.
够了
- Nasty language these crows have.  - Yes.
- 这吉普赛鸟语真心难听要死  - 对啊
Fit for devils, not people.
真的不是给人听的
He only passed by here.
他只是路过这里
Where'd he go, then?
然后去了哪里
Towards Craiova
往克拉约瓦去
or to the next county...
或许到邻近城邦去了
When did he leave?
什么时候走的
Before sunset, many days ago.
太阳下山前 很多天前吧
If you lie to me,we'll spill your guts...
你要敢说谎 我就打死你
I ain't lying, bright lord.
我没说谎 大人
Some bear-taming Gypsies passed by
一些有驯熊的吉普赛人过去之后
then your man
就是你说的这个人
My boys gave him some foodand
我儿子给了他一点吃的
off he went.
然后他就离开了
If you've been crowing out lies,
你们要是胆敢撒谎
we'll come back with the posse and kill you like sparrows.
我会带人过来灭了你们所有人
Bright lord, here's some gold, so you won't leave angry.
大人 这里有些黄金 你也别生气
Damn you and your gold!
去你妈蛋的黄金
Ionita, this is how you scare the crows,
欧尼塔 要吓这群吉普赛佬就得这样
if you're a man!
是男人就要像这样
Yes.
了解
A good butcher doesn't fear thousands of thousands of sheep!
一匹狼还怕啥一千头羊
Fucking bad luck! A priest in skirts.
运气真背 遇到个穿裙子的修士
Ten years of misfortune.
一背背一生啊
Away, Satan
撒旦
Why do we do that?
我们为什么会这样
'Cause devils flock around priests.
因为恶魔总跟着修士
What happened, honourable Father?
怎么了 敬爱的神父
This cursed wheel broke off.
这个破轮子坏了
Shall we help, like good Samaritans?
要我们帮忙吗
God bless you. The snakes would have swallowed me alive.
上帝保佑你 别是来落井下石的
God is glad to see two poor souls helping each other.
上帝欣慰于落难者互相帮助
You have an axe there and all you need.
你要有把斧头就够了
What are you looking for?
你们在找谁啊
A runaway Gypsy slave who stole the boyar's money.
一个偷了钱跑路的吉普赛奴隶
Damned crow!
没脑子的吉普赛佬
I didn't see anyone. So he ran away?
我没看到任何人 他真跑了吗
Yes, Father. The crows have no shame anymore.
是的神父 这些人毫无羞耻心
It'll be the end of us
只要将他绳之于法
when the ass gets at the head and the cunt is in command...
我们就能结案了…
True, Father.
说真的 神父
I just hope he doesn't run to the Turks.
我只是希望他没跑去土耳其
What could he do there?
他在那能干嘛
He could become a mercenary in Nicopolis.
他去了尼可波立也会有人雇用啊
If he does, we've lost him...
如果这样 那就找不到他了…
Ready, Father.
好了 神父
God, bless Thy servants, amen!
上帝会保佑他的子民 阿门
Have some holy water.
饮点圣水吧
To wash us of our many sins...
来洗涤我们身上诸多罪恶…
Good for you.
这样很好
As the Ecclesiastes says:
如传道书所言
"Whatsoever thy hand findeth to do,do it with thy might;
凡你手所当作的事 要尽力去作
for there is no work
因为在你所必去的阴间 没有工作
nor device,nor knowledge, nor wisdom,
没有谋算 没有知识
in the grave, where thou goest."
也没有智慧
Well said, my sons! Christ did not rise in vain.
说的好孩子们 耶稣没有白复活了
So help us God!
上帝 来帮助我们吧
I'll spend the night at Manjoala's inn.
我会在曼卓拉的驿站过夜
I never travel in the dark for fear of outlaws.
我从不在土匪当道的黑夜赶走
As for us,first business, then pleasure:
对我们来说 工作第一 享乐倒是其次
we'll search 'til the Seven Sisters rise...
我们要持续搜寻到看见北斗星升起
Isn't there a holiday coming, Father?
是不是就到假期了 神父
So it is.
是啊
Forgive me, Lord! I hanged You with thread,
原谅我 我只给您挂上丝线
and not with a gold chain, like the bishops.
不用金链 就像主教
But isn't it faith that matters most?
但信仰不是最重要的吗
Faith, but also deeds!
信仰很重要 但行为也很重要
Another question, if we may?
还能提出其他问题吗
Sure.
当然
You're more enlightened, you have praxis...
您比较睿智 您有实践…
Gypsies, is they people or Satan's spawn?
吉普赛人是人还是恶魔
Some say they ain't human.
有人说他们不是人
Human like us.
像我们一样的人
Aren't they Christians?
难道他们不是天主教徒吗
I myself baptised two slave cubs recently.
我最近就替两个奴隶孩子受洗
Monastery slaves?
修道院的吉普赛人吗
Right, two chickies.
对啊 两个小兔崽子
Crows are descendants of Ham,son of Noah,
这帮人其实是诺亚之子闪的后代
cursed by his father to be black.
因被父亲诅咒而一身漆黑
They came here from Egypt.
他们从埃及来到这里
They are Egyptians.
他们是埃及人
Is that so?
是吗
Yes. What do we call crows to mock them?
是啊 我们怎么嘲笑他们的
Black crows.
黑乌鸦
There are no white crows. How else?
乌鸦是没白色的 还有其他的吗
Maggots.
蛆虫
- What else?  - Darkies.
- 还有呢  - 黑仔
Pharaohs.
法老
Good, aferim! Pharaohs
对的 吉普赛法老
'Cause they came here from Egypt,
他们因为来自埃及
where they were also slaves,building palaces for the kings.
在那儿他们也是奴隶 替国王盖宫殿的
When a wise man opens his mouth, open your ears!
智者大开金口 你得洗耳恭听
Gypsies is humans.Jews ain't.
吉普赛人是人 犹太人才不是
They's beasts.
他们是野兽
If you say so...
你这么说也太…
Now you tell me,why is Jews not human?
不然你说犹太人为何是人
'Cause Jews drinks the blood of Christian children.
因为犹太人会喝天主教孩子的血
The priest told us so in church.
教堂里的神父跟我们这样说过
And why do they?
他们为什么这么做
We don't know.
我们哪儿知道
Have you heard of the Giant Jews?
你有听说过犹太巨人吗
No.
没有
Shame on you...
你真丢脸…
Before making mankind,God created the Giant Jews.
上帝造人之前 先造了犹太巨人
Mean, ugly giants.
刻薄而又丑陋的巨人
He saw His mistake and turned them into dust.
他发现搞错了 然后就把他们化为尘土
He left just a few,then made Adam and Eve.
只留下几个 然后才创造亚当夏娃
The Giant Jews multiplied,but grew ever smaller.
犹太巨人开始复制 体型越来越小
They's our Jews nowadays.
才成了今日的犹太人
We didn't know that.
这些我们从没听过
That's why Jews can't stand us Christians,
所以犹太人受不了我们基督信徒
that's why they killed Christ.
因此他们才杀了耶稣
And that's why I can't stand them.
因此我也就受不了他们
Do you know what I do with pork-haters?
你们知道我是怎么对付不吃猪肉的人的吗
We don't.
不知道
I cut off their beards and sidelocks.
剃掉他们的胡子跟两侧小辫子
Better a Jew without a beard than a beard without a Jew!
没胡须的犹太人好过有留胡须的人
Do you know what they do in Moldova?
你知道他们在摩多瓦怎么干的吗
I don't know...
我不知道
Jews walk around in their carriages.
犹太人以车代步
And instead of horses
但不是用马拉车
they use good Christians.
而是叫善良的基督信徒来拉
I don't believe it, father.That's what the Russians did to us.
我不信 俄罗斯人才会对我们这样
In the war of 1828,
一八二八年的那场战争中
General Zaltukhin harnessed our peasants...
佐洛图辛将军统治我们的农民…
The Christians in my cousin's village
我表弟村里的基督信徒们
can't bleed themselves
养活不了自己
the Jews left no leeches in the lake.
犹太人就拚命压榨他们
But some Jews are baptised into our Christian faith.
但也有些犹太人受洗成了基督信徒
Who would believe those outlaws?
谁会相信那些恶徒
"Who makes up the Devil's flocks? "
谁是恶魔的党羽
"All the Jews with their sidelocks."
那些留辫子的犹太人
Each nation has its purpose.
每个国家都有自己的宗旨
The Jews, to cheat
对犹太人而言 是欺骗
the Turks, to do harm,
土耳其人来说 是伤害
us Romanians to love, honour
我们罗马尼亚人则是爱 荣耀
and suffer like good Christians.
和如同优秀基督信徒般的受苦
And each has their habits.
各个民族有各自的秉性
Hebrews reads a lot
希伯来人喜欢读书
Greeks talks a lot,
希腊人喜欢说话
Turks has many wives,
土耳其人拥有很多老婆
Arabs has many teeth,
阿拉伯人伶牙俐齿
Germans smokes a lot
德国人喜欢抽烟
Hungarians eats a lot
匈牙利人喜欢暴食
Russians drinks a lot,English thinks a lot,
俄罗斯人喜欢喝酒 英国人喜欢思考
French like fashion a lot,Armenians are lazy,
法国人喜欢赶时髦 亚美尼亚人喜欢懒散
Circasians wears many a lace,
索西亚人喜欢蕾丝
Italians lies a lot,
意大利人喜欢撒谎
Serbians cheats a lot.
塞尔维亚人喜欢骗人
and Gypsies get many a beating
吉普赛人喜欢被骗
Gypsies must be slaves.
吉普赛人注定得当奴隶
When Ham spread horse shit on Noah,
当闪对着诺亚泼马粪时
Noah cursed them to be slaves
诺亚诅咒他们永为奴隶
and as dark as shit.
并且长得跟屎一样黑
That's right.
这倒是真的
They must be kept on a tight leash.'Tis a holy commandment.
他们得严格管教 用十诫加以规范
But with kindness.That is my habit.
但凡事仁心待之 这是我的秉性
Though I'm as harsh as a hot pepper
虽然我的严厉
born of father Garlic and mother Onion.
如同大蒜洋葱混合的辣椒一般呛人
I treat people kindly.
但我对人却是满满的善意
The Gospel says to be as gentle as doves, Father...
福音书上说 要像鸽子般温柔
If the beasts weren't vanquished,
野兽若不被制伏
they would tear man apart.
它们终会撕裂我们
Even among people,most are beasts
就算人类之间 也藏有野兽
who must be tamed to make them work.
亟需驯服 方能工作
Particularly the crows.
特别是那帮吉普赛人
Lovely thoughts, Father.
很有趣的想法 神父
We'll head this way.
我们要往这边走了
We wish you good health.
祝您身体健康
Good health to bear good grief.
不惧悲苦
Go with God, we may meet again.
心随上帝 或许会再相遇
The mountains themselves sometimes meet...
人生何处不相逢…
True words.
至理名言啊
Even a fallen tree rests...
树倒了是得休息
It's not true, Ionita.
这不对 欧尼塔
You could walk until you die
你可用用尽一生行走
and still not touch the end of the Earth.
依然无法触及世界尽头
That's what the priest told us:
所以神父才说
that the Earth has an edge,it ain't endless.
宇宙是无穷有界的
Those are just a fool's teachings.
那些都是迂腐的教诲
Father Duhu told us everything has an end but for God,
杜胡神父言 世事有涯 唯上帝无尽
who has neither beginning, nor end.
无始亦无终
Doesn't the Earth have an end?
难道宇宙没有边界吗
Where it ends, ain't it like a precipice?
到了尽头 还不是如同悬崖断层
I don't know.'Tain't any of my concern.
我不知道 我也不关心
I have other worries.
我有其他的事要操心
We're nothing, Ionita.
或许我们什么都不是 欧尼塔
Look at the size of this world...
看看这世界之大
...we're like a spark from these embers.
我们就像星火残渣
Do you know the seven planets?
你知道七大行星吗
The Moon, the Sun...
月亮 太阳
Bottle, Flask, Pitcher, Mug, Carafe, Jar, and Stein.
酒瓶 酒壶 酒罐 酒杯 酒桶 酒盅…
Here I lay and die,No help by my side.
我若死在此地 何人救我
Far as I may seek,My fate remains bleak.
道路漫漫 命运蹉跎
Life of grief and sorrow, No hope for tomorrow.
悲喜哀怨 人生无望
Some have luck, fortune and fame,
幸者似功成名就
Some burn like the candle's flame!
悲者如残灯泯灭
What's gotten into you?
你怎么了
Do you like Aspra?
你喜欢雅丝帕吗
She's a hard-working girl...
她是个认真工作的女孩
How could I like that slob?
我怎会喜欢那个傻女孩
You know, as a girl.
我是说单就女人而言
Nah, I don't like her.
不 我不喜欢她
You're not a Sodomite, are you?
你喜欢后入对不对
What's that?
什么意思
Liking men, not women...
就是喜欢爆菊 不爱女人…
No such thing.
没有的事
'Cause if you are,
因为要是你是的话
I'll drown you with my own hands.
我会亲手把你给淹死
What's that?
那是啥
The haidouks!
有土匪
Or the savage Gypsies.
也可能是吉普赛人
There's also bullet wounds. It was the haidouks.
他们有枪伤 是土匪
Let's make way.
快离开
- Father...  - Keep that mouth shut!
- 父亲…  - 别出声
- One was breathing.  - Sure he was.
- 有个人还有呼吸  - 我觉得是
He moved just now.
他刚刚动了一下
What are we, surgeons?
我们是谁啊 医生吗
May he rest in peace.
愿他安息吧
We're safe.
我们安全了
Fear is shameful, but healthy.
害怕虽然有点耻辱 但是无碍
It's God's gift.
这是上帝的恩赐
You whore's son, watch where you're going!
操你大爷的 不会看路啊
Is this your own path? Stay the hell in a row!
这路你家的吗 不会照规矩走
Fuck your mother!
操你妈的
Find a dog to fuck you, moron!
日了狗吧 脑残
The rich man is like a hare,
有钱人跟野兔一样
he leaps wherever he wants to.
想跳哪儿就跳哪儿
Maybe a big landowner or a Greek boyar.
估计是个土豪或希腊贵族
Still, he should watch where he's going.
再怎样还是得看路啊
That's our fate as Romanians!
这就是我们罗马尼亚人的宿命
Whoever rises earliest can drag you by your hair.
只要在你上头就可以欺负你
May he live three more days, counting yesterday!
祝他只能活三天 昨天也算进去
So pretty!
好美啊
Fuck your prettiness!
美你妈蛋
Peace to you, good fellow.
你好 老兄
Good day.
你好
We're looking for a runaway crow, a Gypsy slave.
我们在找一个逃跑中的吉普赛奴隶
I'm a peasant here, but I ain' seen nobody.
我在这边种地 没看到任何人
You ain't gonna find him.
你找不到他的
Like they didn't find the runaways from our monastery.
他们在我的修道院也没找到逃犯
Would you sell us some fish?
可以卖些鱼给我吗
Why not?
有啥不可以的
Maybe he's in the forest, with the gold panners.
说不定他跟淘金客躲进森林里了
He ain't.
他没有
Then I don't know, constable.
那我就不清楚了
But the monks would have seen him here.
但僧侣们有见到他在这儿
I think so too. Is there a way across through the reeds?
我想也是 芦苇丛那里有路吗
They's too thick.
那边很茂密
What if we go around?
如果绕路走呢
- Two days.  - Too long.
- 得花上两天  - 太久了
Look at this!
你看
Constable, the money?
警察 钱呢
That's very little, constable.
怎么这么少
It ain't worth more.
再多值不了
Come on... constable...
拜托
We can cross, the water is shallow.
过得去 水很浅
Curse this wretched craft!
什么狗屁
Crawling along, mocked by everyone.
还得自己游泳 说了会被大家取笑
This is a dog's life.
简直比狗还不如
We sweat like beasts for a piece of bread.
为了点芝麻小事辛苦得要死
If I had had the luck of joining this new army...
我要运气够好加入新军队的话
- n't they take you in now?
他们现在不收你吗
No, curse them...
不收
But if you learn all the tricks of the constable job from me,
但要是你跟着我学到警察各种技能
I'll get you into the army.
我就有办法把你弄进军队
Let's go back, we can't pass.
我们回去吧 过不去的
By thirty you'll be a colonel.
那你三十岁就能当上校了
You're full of fire and fierce.
保证你意气风发
But you're also lazy...
但你也挺懒的…
No, I ain't.
不 我才没有
You have to be quick like gunpowder.
你得像枪炮一般快
Who are you?
来的是谁
I'm lawkeeper Costandin sin Gheorghe.
我是康斯坦丁警察
He's my boy, he helps me.
这是我儿子 来帮我的
What's your business here?
你在这里想干嘛
We're looking for a runaway Gypsy.
我们在追捕一个逃亡的吉普赛人
What Gypsy?
什么吉普赛人
Where's your mandate?
你的逮捕令在哪
No good, it's not from our ruler.
这不行 不符合我们的规定
I didn't find the Gypsy in my county...
我们这里没看到什么吉普赛人
This is Dumbrava county.
这里是杜巴瓦城邦
I give the orders here.
此地的规矩由我来订
You get me a mandate, and I'll seek him for you.
那你给我逮捕令 我把他找给你
What if I get one from your ruler?
如果我按你的规定申请逮捕令呢
We'll see then.
那再说吧
Come on, we're two good lawmen...
拜托  我们俩都是治安官…
Go back!
滚回去
Come over here.
过来一下
What for?
要干嘛
Let's have a word.
聊一下
What would it take for us to agree?
怎样才能得到你的批准
You say.
你说
I give you two thalers and you let me look for him.
给你两泰勒币 让我把他找出来
These are hard times, bey-mu...
世道不同啊…
The Russians struck at us, too...
俄国人也在攻击我们…
How much, then?
那你开个价
Four thalers, and I'll even tell you where the crow's hiding.
四泰勒 我会告诉你那家伙躲哪儿
- Where is he, then?  - Money first, bey-mu.
- 他在哪  - 先给钱再说
Four.
四泰勒
He's in the house of an ugly man, Stan sin Paraschiv by name.
他躲在一个名叫史丹的丑男屋里
He's a basket weaver.
是做篮子的
How do I find him?
那我该怎么找过去
Go back, past some hovels,
往回走 经过几间茅屋
then you'll see a house by the pond.
池塘边有间房子就是
Thanks a-plenty. We're sick of chasing this crow,
多谢啦 我们追这家伙都追烦了
I'm also sick and coughing...
我自己都生了病咳嗽…
No scandal, bey-mu.
别出乱子啊
'Pon my honour! I'm a constable too!
别担心 我也是警察
You haven't heard it from me.
我没跟你说这事
If we don't know the miserable life we lead,
自己要不知道处境悲惨
who does?
还有谁会知道
I'm in your debt.
我欠你的
If you need anything else, ask for me.
有需要再来问我
Many thanks.
多谢
Go see why that hag ran off.
去看看那家伙为什么跑
...I'll crack your head open with my yatagan.
…看我用刀劈开你的脑袋
There's nothing here.
啥都没有
Get the hell away!
滚开
A constable is here!
警察来了
Bright lords, what is your need?
大人 您在找什么啊
Good day, aunt,we're looking for Stan sin Paraschiv.
你好 我找史丹
- What for?  - We have a word with him.
- 有何贵干  - 问他几句话
- What word?  - A joke.
- 问什么话  - 小事
A joke.
笑话
Oi, you're crushing me!
吃老娘豆腐
What are you looking for?
你在找什么
You're ruining our reed!
你弄坏我们芦苇了
Good man Stan Burned down the barn...
好人史丹把谷仓给烧了
What do you want with me, constable?
警察 找我有事吗
I am lawkeeper Costandin sin Gheorghe.
我是康斯坦丁警察
We're here to seize Carfin,the Gypsy slave in your house.
奉命追拿躲在你这的奴隶…卡芬
Here's our mandate.
这是追捕令
He's my son.
这是我儿子
I can't afford Gypsies.
我才买不起吉普赛人
What am I, a boyar?
你以为我是贵族吗
We break our backs working for nothing.
累死累活却赚不到钱
How could we own Gypsies?
怎么养得起吉普赛人
We know he's here.
我们知道他在这
- Who?  - The crow.
- 谁  - 那王八蛋
What crow?
到底是谁
Boyar Candescu's Gypsy.
坎德斯古公爵的吉普赛奴隶
We have no such boyar around here.
我们这里没这个贵族
He's playing the idiot, isn't he, Ionita?
装傻是吧 欧尼塔
He is.
他是
- Me, playing the idiot?  - Yes.
- 我装傻  - 对
- Me, having a Gypsy here?  - Yes.
- 我雇了个吉普赛  - 对
I tell him I'm a nun and he takes off my habit...
我还说我是修女 他把我衣服脱了…
- I don't have any!  - Yes, you do.
- 我没有啊  - 你有
Good Lord, where is he, then?
大人 那他在哪呢
Wherever you hid him.
你把他藏起来了啊
Should I put the Lord's whip on your back?!
要我拿大人的鞭子抽你吗
Do you see any Gypsy? A pig it's all we have.
你有看到吉普赛人吗 我们就只有头猪
No Gypsy! This is a poor household.
没有吉普赛 这里是穷苦人家
It doesn't look that poor.
看起来不穷啊
We're dirt poor, we only have the skin on our backs.
我们穷死了 穷到只剩皮包骨
You still have the fortune between your legs!
裤裆里都是金元宝吧
Bless you!
上帝保佑
Diddle, diddle, the cat and the fiddle!
藏藏藏
Let's play piggy in the middle!
看看谁在骗人
Just a little neighbourhood crow.
他只是临近的一个吉普赛人
Let's search some more.
让我们再找找
See? No one here.
看到没 没人
My daughter-in-law, old Grandpa on his deathbed.
就我媳妇 还有卧病在床的爷爷
Woman, bring a candle!
拿蜡烛来
- What's here?  - Never seen an attic before?
- 那是什么  - 阁楼还没吧
Where we keep our baskets, beans, onion...
就储藏室 摆些篮子 大蒜和洋葱
Where do you think you're climbing?
你想爬哪儿去
Are you hitting a lawkeeper?
你要打治安官吗
He's killed me!
有人要杀人啊
Father!
父亲
He's killin' me!
杀人啦
Let him go!
放开他
I'll buy him from you!
我跟你把他买回来
Help, they's killin' me!
救命啊 杀人啊
Stay away or I shoot!
走开 否则我开枪了
It ain't me. Let me go!
不是我 放我走
Let him go, he's Stan's slave!
让他走 他是史丹的奴隶
Where are you from, blackie?
你哪来的 小黑仔
Master Iancu the merchant.
商人蓝苏大人那儿
Ran away from there?
也是跑出来的吗
Yes, master, 'cause he beat me bad.
对 因为他打我
And he stabbed my brother to death when he was drunk.
他喝醉时把我哥捅死了
I got scared and I ran.
吓到我我才跑的
What's your name?
你叫什么名字
Tintiric, master.
丁提利 大人
How old are you?
你几岁
How should I know?
我怎么知道
Hasn't anyone told you?
没人告诉过你吗
No, master.
没有
Stop shaking like a hag's teeth, are you scared?
别抖个不停 你怕了吗
Yes, master.
对
Shut up!
闭嘴
What's the matter?
怎么了
This shitskin wanted to flee.
这狗屎想跑
I didn't.
我没有
You wanted to jump off.
你想下马
We're taking him back.
带他回去
The merchant might thank us with a dime or two.
那商人兴许会赏个一块两块
Don't take me back!
别让我回去
Upon my life, master. He'll beat me!
我发誓 他一定会打我的
Shut up, little prince,or I'll smack you.
闭嘴 小王子  小心我抽你大嘴巴子
Father, he's just a poor soul!
爸 他好可怜啊
A devil's soul... But the devil can bring in money, too.
魔鬼可怜的屁…倒是可以拿来赚钱
Right.
也对
We know your kind.
我们知道你是好人
You all say you didn't steal.
你们都说自己没偷
I didn't, kind lord...
我真的没有…
Why did you flee, then?
那你为什么跑
Is it better now?
不然怎么办
Don't turn me over to the boyar, master.
别把我带回去 大人
He'll kill me. Take me as your slave.
他会杀了我 让我做你的奴隶吧
I'll do all you say, just don't take me back.
我会为你做任何事 只要不带我回去
- He won't kill you...  - Yes he will.
- 他不会杀你的  - 他会
Fish brains in a rabbit's head...
以小人之心度君子之腹
He'll give you a beating and send you back to work.
他会打你 再送你回去做工
Where a boyar strikes, new skin grows.
有贵族鞭策才有长进
- Ain't that right, Tintiric?  - Right.
- 对不对 丁提利  - 对的
On our street,
我们那条街
a trader buried a man alive and the man died.
有个商人埋了个活人就死了
- What trader?  - Kir Costea.
- 哪个商人  - 克尔寇司提
He buried a man alive, many people saw.
他活埋的时候很多人都看到了
What had he done?
他做什么了
No one told me.
没人告诉我
At least if I were guilty. But I ain't.
要是我有罪也就罢了 问题是我没有
Who else could be guilty? Me?
那是谁有罪 我吗
His wife pushed me to fuck her.
是他老婆勾引的我
Hear that, Ionita,
你听听看 欧尼塔
the crow claims he fucked the boyar's woman.
这家伙声称自己干了公爵夫人
Swear upon the devil's cod, upon Aaron's rod,
我发誓
so help you God!
上帝帮我吧
So how'd she push you, crow?
那她怎么勾引的你
She had her eyes set on me since they had bought me.
她从买下我就一直盯着我
But I couldn't believe...
但难以置信的是…
One day, I was watering the horses...
有一天 我在洗马
She came quietly into the stables,
她偷偷溜进马厩
hop! she climbed on top of me
然后扑到我身上
and rubbed her cunt against my nape.
用她的阴部摩擦我的丁丁
The old hen ain't scared of a thick cock!
门锁可不担心钥匙的硬
So you didn't like it?!
你不喜欢吧
I did, aren't I a man?
喜欢啊 我还是个男人吗
The things I did to her...
我对她做的那些事…
And if I hadn't liked it? She's my mistress.
我怎能不喜欢 她可是我的女主人
Then why'd you run from such grief, crow?
所以才被吓跑了 是不是
The stable boy found out and told the boyar,
马厩小伙计发现后就告诉了公爵
who said he'd kill me... I ran for my life.
他要杀我…为了活命我就跑路了
- He's making it up!  - I'm not, good master...
- 他开始编故事了  - 我没有
I've heard about the lady's fornication,
我听说过那女人
even with her cousin.
连跟表哥都通奸
They even say she bore his child.
流言甚至还说她生了他的孩子
I knew from the start this wasn't a clear business.
我一开始就感觉这事情不简单
What did I say?
我能怎么说
Two turtledoves in sweet love's fires, eh?
一对儿干柴烈火吗
Who had time for that...
谁有那种时间啊…
Curse them Turks.
去他的土耳其人
How to get to Licheresti? I know.
如何去利切瑞斯提 我知道
Mind your words!
管住你的嘴
He's my boy, he helps me.
他是我儿子 他来帮我的
He wants to give you a gift.
他说想给你一个礼物
Say tesekkur.
跟人家说谢谢
I want some.
我也想要
- What'd he want?  - To get to Licheresti.
- 他想怎样  - 想去利切瑞斯提
I sent the fool the other way.
我给这蠢货指了另一条道
Aferim, father!
干得好 父亲
I hate the Ottomans. The filthiest nation on Earth.
我恨奥图曼人 世上最下流的国家
And he talked to me like I was shit.
跟我讲话时说得我跟屎一样
Said he was afraid of the haidouks...
说不定他是怕吉普赛人…
I hope our Romanian boys catch him
我希望罗马尼亚人能抓到他
and tan his skin.
扒了他的皮
They should.
对啊
You can tell from their talk that they's nothin' but beasts.
听他们讲话就知道他们就是一群野兽
- Give me some.  - Fine, have some.
- 给我一点  - 好啊 你来一点
We work like morons for them and the boyars...
我们为他们简直在当牛做马
It's closer...
快到了
We can do some good business,without wasting time.
可以做些好交易 别浪费时间
Look what I found for you, cricket.
你看我抓了什么给你 蟋蟀
You can find ripe fruit under the driest leaf.
枯叶下可以找到成熟的果实
Master, don't take me back!
大人 别送我回去
Bey-mu, what can I do?
混蛋 我能怎么办
Clap my hands and make you a divan-effendi?!
把你当神一样供起来吗
Take me to your home!
把我带回家
I can work the fields, cook...
我能在田里劳作 还能做饭
I don't need that. I have a wife.
我不需要 我有老婆
Have pity, bright lord.
可怜可怜我吧 大人
Be thankful I don't beat you.
没打你就已经算是很可怜你了
I give you a finger, don't ask for the whole hand.
你可别得寸进尺了
You struck bad luck.
你迟早让我倒霉
But I had my good days too.
我也有撞大运的时候
When?
啥时候
When I was a slave for his highness Bibescu.
当我还是毕博斯殿下奴隶的时候
Then, when he died,
不过他死了以后
for his highness Manu and Lady Smaranda Vacarescu.
我就过给了曼纽小姐跟珊曼莎太太
- Lies, Gypsy.  - I swear!
- 你骗人  - 我发誓
I was looking after the horses...
我当时在看管马匹…
I even went with him to Paris, to Leipzig.
还跟他去过巴黎 莱比锡
To Vienna, too...
还有维也纳…
I've seen the world.
我可是有见过世面的
Did you fuck Lady Smaranda, too?
你跟珊曼莎太太做过吗
No way!
不可能
She hardly even looked at us Gypsies,
她看都不看我们吉普赛人
she only talked with her sly crones...
她只跟老太婆说话…
So, how does lady Sultana go when she fucks?
那跟索坦娜太太做起来感觉怎样
Does she moan and move?
她叫床吗 动作大不
She moves her big buttocks hard.
她屁股摇得很用力
She doesn't moan, for fear someone might hear...
倒是不敢大声叫 怕被人听到…
And she whispered in my ear:
她会在我耳旁说
"Psihi-mu, I like your cock so! Stick it deeper!"
我喜欢你的大丁丁 再捅进去点
And after I let myself go,
当我完事之后
she'd whisper:
她则会说
"Mashallah, Gypsy!"
好爽啊 吉普赛佬
I see...
我懂了
So how's the world?
外头的世界怎么样
Big and beautiful... Not like here.
又大又美…不像这里
He knows his stuff!
他知道自己的事
So, what's it like in Vienna?
那…说说维也纳吧
I've never left our county except for father's work.
除了跟父亲工作 我从没出过国
I don't know what to say...
不知该怎么形容啊…
Like three of our towns, only with palaces.
大概有我们三个镇子大  还有个宫殿
How 'bout Leipzig?
那莱比锡呢
It's smaller. But prettier than anything here.
比较小 但也比这儿美
And Paris?
巴黎呢
Big, like ten Viennas...
很大 像维也纳…
Cobbled roads, countless princesses.
卵石铺的路 公主满街都是
And they don't beat their servants.
也不会打他们的仆人
Lies!
胡扯什么
It ain't lies!
我没胡扯
When lady Manu married that dumb Russian prince,
当曼纽小姐嫁给那个愚蠢的俄国王子时
she asked as dowry for a Vienna carriage.
她就要了一辆维也纳马车当嫁妆
In exchange we, thirty souls of Gypsies,
用我们三十个吉普赛奴隶
were given to boyar Filipescu.
来跟菲力伯公爵做交换
The beatings we got there with ox sinews...
一到那边我们先挨了顿皮鞭暴打…
Three months ago, master Filipescu auctioned away
三个月前 菲力伯大人
some five hundred Gypsy souls.
就交易了五百个吉普赛奴隶
Master Candescu bought me from him.
坎德斯古公爵从他那买了我
I asked him to buy my family too...
我则求他一起买了我家人
We have no concern with your life...
我们不在乎你的人生…
We're hardworking...
我们努力工作…
Make Way!
让开
What's this?
这是什么
Vasilache and Marioara.
木偶戏啊
I'm a man, not a mouse.
我是人 不是老鼠
Take this, if you're a man!
要是你是个男人就吞了这个
'Tis like they's real men.
好像真人啊
No, you dimwit, they's dolls
你是不是傻 那是玩偶而已
with people moving them!
要人操控的
Crack the stupid bitch's head!
打爆这婊子的脑袋
Will you be quiet now?
你可以闭嘴了吗
Now she's upset. Get up, Marioara!
她生气了 起来吧 玛莉娜
Fuck her!
干她
Shut up! She's dead
闭嘴 她死了
The priest!
神父
...let's give her a funeral!
…我们替她办场葬礼吧
What funeral? You're drunk!
什么葬礼 你喝醉了
Go to hell with your Marioara!
跟你的玛莉娜一起下地狱吧
Look at him beating that priest!
你看他都打神父了
Whosoever buys us,
不管谁买我们
we will be slaves to his house,
我们就会是他的奴隶
we and our offspring,
我们跟我们的后代
just save us from hunger...
只要让我们不挨饿就行…
Back off, everyone!
通通退后
Take pity on me, master!
可怜可怜我吧 大人
Didn't you say you don't want to go back to the merchant?
你不是说不想回到商人身边
Who will buy me?
谁会买我啊
might end up with one who will beat me to death.
搞不好会遇到一个人把我打死
We'll find you a good man.
我们会帮你找个好人家
We won't give you to just anyone.
不会把你随便卖人
Good, then...
那好吧
Buy me, honourable lords!
买了我吧 大人
I'm a hardworking, obedient slave!
我是努力又听话的奴隶
Take us, master! We are freed slaves.
买我们吧 我们还没有主人
- How many of you?  - A clan.
- 你们几个人  - 一家人
Back off!
滚开
How much?
卖多少
Almost nothing. Ten piastres.
很便宜 十斯特
Expensive! For that I can buy two big ones.
太贵了 这价钱我可以买两个大人
This is the price of the market. I know the worth of a slave...
这就是市场行情 我知道行情
Let me see your beak, crow.
我看一下你的嘴 吉普赛佬
Doesn't even have all his teeth.
连牙齿都没长齐
Bey-mu, they'll grow. He's a child.
他是孩子 还没张开
Thin as a rake, too.
瘦得皮包骨似的
No, he has iron bones.
哪有 他强壮得像块铁板
He's sturdy stock.
肯定无坚不摧
Come to the scalesmaster.
过来秤一下
What for?
干嘛
To see how much he weighs.
看看他有多重
- Where is he?  - There.
- 他在哪  - 在那
Where are you taking me, master?
你要带我去哪儿 大人
Buy us, bright lords!
收了我们吧 大人
Three stone and a half.
三个半石头重
See, he's in excellent condition.
看到没 他很壮的
I want to give him to our holy church.
我想把他献给我们的教堂
Drop it three piastres.
三斯特开不开
No more than one.
再添点
Do you have papers? Or is he stolen?
你有证明吗 还是偷来的
No one will find him. I'm a lawkeeper.
没人能找得到他 我就是治安官
Without papers, four piastres.
没证明就四斯特
What is he, a chicken? He's a slave!
你当他是啥 鸡吗 他是个奴隶
Let's see who will give you more.
我们再看看谁愿意再出高价
At least five.
至少五斯特
Deal.
成交
Don't give me away, master!
别把我给别人 大人
They're not forged, are they?
这不是假币吧
How much for the one on the horse?
马背上的这个卖多少
Two piastres.
两斯特
He's not for sale.
他不卖的
A pity, he was a good one. Come on, crow!
真可惜 他还不错 跟我走 吉普赛佬
Good luck, Tintiric!
祝你好运 丁提利
What are you meddling for?
你在瞎操心什么
Father! Come on up!
父亲 过来
No, it's not for me.
不 那不适合我
Come on!
来嘛
- Is that good?  - Yes!
- 这个好玩吗  - 好玩
Amazing!
太棒了
Money wasted...
浪费钱
What can I do, Carfin? You made your own bed.
卡芬我能怎样 自作孽不可活啊
Have pity, constable,
可怜可怜我吧 警察
set me free! Ionita!
给我自由吧 欧尼塔
I can't deceive the boyar...
我不能欺骗公爵…
But I'll tell him how that bitch jumped you...
但我会告诉公爵他那婊子勾搭你…
He will lock her up in some convent.
他会把她软禁在修女院
So what? He'll still kill me.
能顶啥用 他还是会杀了我
Enough whining, he won't kill you.
你叫够了没 他不会杀你的
I'll ask him to just beat you a little.
我会叫他打你一下就好了
He'll kill me, master!
他会杀我的 大人
Will you buy me some sweets?
可以买点糖给我吗
No money for that.
没钱
Come on, crow!
走吧 吉普赛佬
How much to sleep here?
睡一晚几块
Twenty for a man, five for a horse.
一个二十 马的话五块
Bring us ham and some cheap wine.
给我们一些火腿 再拿些便宜的酒
A starving dog dreams of nothing but bones.
饿死鬼做梦也只会梦到饭
- Lica ate, drank, and didn't pay.  - Nevermind.
- 又是吃又是喝却不掏钱  - 没关系
What did that crow do?
那奴隶做了什么
Ran away from a boyar.
从公爵家逃跑了
If he was my crow,
他要是我的奴隶
I'd have blinded him and cut off his legs.
我就戳瞎他眼睛 打断他双腿
Go to hell!
去死吧
Dig in.
吃吧
The rich look in the mirror,the poor  - in their plate.
有钱人照镜子 穷人只能照盘子
Damn good.
说得好
You're badly ill, father.
你病得不轻啊 父亲
I have this nixis in my chest.
我的胸口很闷
My teeth rattle,the shovel is waiting...
牙齿松动 一条腿算是迈进鬼门关了
How about the doctors in Bucharest?
布加勒斯特的大夫如何
It's your turn to live, Ionita...
现在是你的时代 欧尼塔
Feels like yesterday I was servingunder bailiff Vladimirescu.
我仿佛昨天还在警队服役…
What a life, fuck...
人生啊 卧槽
Sigh louder, crow!
再大点声啊 死吉普赛佬
I was storming women away during the uprising.
我革命的时候 还攻击过女人
We would enter a village,
我们进入一个村庄
kill their cattle and party wildly...
杀了他们的牛 有部分还是野生的…
When was that?
什么时候的事
Around 1821. You were a babe.
一八二一年 那年你还是个孩子
You know what our song was?
你知道我们当时的主题歌吗
no
不知道
Seven vales and seven hills.
七个威尔士七座山
Fuck the boyars to the gills
去你妈的大头兵
Soon I'll catch you by the mane,Mash you bloody with my cane...
我会逮到你的鬃毛 一权杖叫你头破血流
We were feared, we killed them like pigs.
那时我们很怕 把他们当猪杀
We were as wild as leopards.
我们同时也像豹子般狂野
I was a mercenary...
我当时是个雇佣兵…
I had a cunt in every village. Don't tell your mother!
每到一村就上个女的 这事别跟你妈说
Sure.
当然
You're a big boy now.
你现在长大成人了
You know how crazy she gets.
知道她抓狂起来有多可怕
My life's all done...
我人生就这样了…
All our lives flow like a stream,
人生宛若一条长河
It all passes like a dream.
随梦一般消逝无踪
Eat some!
吃点吧
The good stuff passed like the wind.
一切美好终将随风而逝
Want a drop of wine?
来点酒吗
Sure!
当然
While drunk, don't give gifts, nor do harm.
醉酒之时 勿施人好 亦勿施人恶
If you do want to give, then give while sober.
欲施人好 等酒醒之时
Hey, innkeeper!
老板
Bring us a whore.
替我们找个妓女
Right away.
马上来
Zambila, get over here!
桑比拉 来这儿
I don't want no Gypsy. I want a clean woman!
不要吉普赛人 我要干净的女人
Clean she is, man.
她很干净
Take my son and do what you know best.
去找我儿子 使出你最好的功夫
I will.
我会的
Innkeeper! I want this pretty one!
老板 我要这个漂亮的
Oi, that's my wife. Let go!
那是我老婆 别碰她
You got the French disease?
你有梅毒吗
Of course not.
肯定没啊
What's your name?
你叫什么
Zambila.
桑比拉
How much for you?
一次多少
Fifteen.
十五块
That's a lot.
太贵了
Come with me!
跟我来
Don't embarrass me, lad.
别让我丢脸 孩子
He's not a bad boy, but he's girlish,
他不坏 只是有点娘
his mother's too soft with him.
他妈太宠爱他了
He's not very respectful...
不太懂人情世故
He's a good lad.
他是个好孩子
That's how I'd like my children to be.
我也希望我孩子也这样
You got children, Carfin?
你有孩子吗 卡芬
No.
没有
Maybe next year, if my wife doesn't die.
或许明年吧 要是我老婆没死的话
You came here from England to teach us your fuckin' ethics?
你从英国过来来教我们这些伦理吗
What's that idiot say?
这傻逼在说啥
You, go away!
你给我滚
Dumb outlanders!
蠢逼外乡人
How's 'bout playing an otuzbir with us?
要不要帮忙打手枪
No.
不要
Then spit on us and let us be.
吐我们口水 然后放过我们
Spit on you?!
吐你们口水吗
I could trim you with this sword.
我倒能用这刀替你整修一番
It's a saying from Targoviste, you know?
这说法源自泰戈维斯特 知道不
Small town, great poverty!
一个破地方 穷乡僻壤的
True, constable.
没错 警察
They say two youngsters went to get married.
听人说两个年轻人在那结婚
But the priest read them the last rites instead.
但神父念的是死前的祷文
Then the baptism rites.
然后是受洗的仪式
When he was supposed to blow over them,
当我们准备要欢送他们时
the youngsters, disgusted with his stupidity, said:
两个年轻人生气地说
"After such a mess,"
早知道要经历这般侮辱
"better spit on us and let us be."
还不如吐我们口水 然后放过我们
Stupid priest! Spit on us and let us be.
笨神父 吐我们口水 然后放过我们
Aferim, Ionita!
干得好 欧尼塔
For a sweet thing like a kiss,
像接吻这般甜美的东西
There's no penance from the priest.
神父是不会禁止的
Right, Father?
对吧 神父
Yes, son.
是的 孩子
- Keep your eye on him.  - Sure.
- 看着他的眼睛  - 好的
How did it go?
情况如何
He's strong like a bull.
他壮得跟头牛一样
Well done!
干得好
You're not all that strong-built.
你们不一定都天生强壮
Were you hatched from an egg?
你怎么跟从蛋孵出来的一样
What can I do?
这又不是我能决定的
Hey, you'll set me on fire.
你会让我烧起来
Tight of cunt and hard of butt, Makes the cock crack like a nut...
丰乳肥臀兮一柱擎天
We'll repent when we're old.
等我们老去之时会慢慢悔悟
Father...
神父
- I'm coming with you.  - Better not.
- 我跟你去  - 最好别吧
There's room for more!
那里没地儿了
Don't know what's wrong with me.
我不知道怎么了
I got a burn in my cock...
我的丁丁好疼
I feel sorry for you, but give me the money.
好可怜啊 但我还得收钱
I didn't?
我又没做成
Only for the boy.
付那孩子那份
Don't scream like a frog in the snake's mouth,I'll pay.
癞蛤蟆嘴叫那么大声干嘛 我给钱就是了
Bite it, crow!
咬吧 死吉普赛佬
Don't make a fool out of me!
别跟我装傻
What's this?
又怎么了
He has to take the dime from the fire.
他得从火里取出来钱
Not with your hand.
不能用手
Take it now!
现在咬
Oh, shut up.
闭嘴
Alas, poor me!
我怎么这么可怜
Who has a stick?
谁有棍子
What for?
要干嘛
These damn rats.
赶老鼠
They's everywhere.
到处都是
And enough lice to shovel them.
还有数不清的跳蚤
A cricket's chirping under my head.
有只蟋蟀在我脸旁叫个不停
Chirp back, then.
到后面去叫
Turn with your head this way.
转个头睡
Father.
父亲
What?
什么
Can't we just let him go?
我们不能放他走吗
Who?
放谁
Carfin. He ain't guilty.
卡芬 他又没犯错
The country's torn apart with prongs
商女不知亡国恨
And the cunt sings merry songs...
隔江犹唱后庭花
What are you, a dean?
你谁啊 司祭长吗
Just thinkin', why should he be punished if he ain't guilty...
你想想他要是没罪为何要受惩罚
Enough with this old maid's dream.
你是给春梦冲昏了头脑
Our job is to catch runaways,
我们的本职是逮捕逃犯
and we caught him.
我们也抓住他了
From here on, there's laws, rules,
国有国法
'tis not for us to pry.
由不得我们
But you're a constable...
但你是警察啊
So what? The law's for everyone.
顶啥用 法律如此 平等视之
We must all follow it.
人人都需遵守
I've been honest all my life. Done my job lawfully.
我一生中时时本分 事事守法
This world's full of evildoers, Ionita.
世界上充满了坏蛋啊
I've seen some freeing locked up thieves at night
我看过一些小偷晚上被放出来
so they could steal horses and cows, then locking them back in...
他们便可以偷马偷牛 然后再关起来
And they shared the loot. I don't do such deeds.
偷的东西还会分赃 我可不这么干
I know.
我知道
And I haven't been mean to folks like other constables.
我也不像别的警察那样为人刻薄
I never beat a soul for nothing.
我从来不会无故打人
I know.
我知道
I've always been fair.
我一直都很公平
If we weren't fair either,
要是连我们都不公平
our country would go straight to Hell.
国家早成地狱了
But I ain't never been black-hearted.
但我从不黑心
I know. What if we said we couldn't find him?
我知道 要是如果我们没找到他呢
Want us to be everyone's laughingstock
你想让我们成为大家笑柄
and not get a single dime?
最后还得不到半毛薪资
You can't feed the wolf and save your lambs.
鱼和熊掌不可兼得啊
Cursed whore's sons, shut those mouths!
去你的 闭嘴
Come on, let's sleep.
快睡吧
Sleep keeps hunger away.
睡着就想不到饿了
My head hurts bad.
我的头好痛
Let me ward off the evil eye from him.
我不想看到他那双魔鬼般的眼睛
Go ahead, Carfin.
去吧 卡芬
He didn't drink much. I drank like a sow,
他没喝多 可我大了
I'm still hazy...
我有点迷糊
Come over here, Ionita!
过来这 欧尼塔
I won't eat you!
我又不吃你
All ache and ail, leave the inside of the head,
抛开所有的悲痛和不快
the hearing of the ears...
还有一切所闻
Shake yourself, Ionita!
孑然一身 欧尼塔
It'll pass, little master, you'll see.
没事 你等会就知道了
O treacherous world, first sweet, then bitter...
操蛋的世界总是先甜后苦…
When the rogues don't set the woods on fire,
要是混混在林里没有防火
we cut them all to the ground.
我们早就把他们全砍了
Wallachia's forests are cracking under the axe...
瓦拉几亚的森林就毁在锄头下
Good country, bad ruling!
这么好的国家 制度却垃圾成屎
I wonder, Ionita,a few hundred years from now,
我在想 几百年之后
d'you think folks will say a good word about us?
后代子孙会赞美我们吗
I don't know, father.
我不知道 父亲
I think they won't say a thing.
我想他们啥都不会说
They won't think that we smoothed their path in life.
他们不会认为我们让他们的人生之路变得平坦
Or they'll only curse our souls to hell.
指不定他们还会诅咒我们下地狱
Gone the day, gone the night...
白日已去 黑夜亦逝
Ease up, constable.
放轻松吧 警察
In two long hours we're home.
两个小时后我们就到家了
We'll get there by dusk.
我们会在黄昏时到那儿
Alas, unjust death and cheating world!
不公的判决和虚假的世界
You bring people comfort, then bury them.
你让人们过得舒服 眨眼又将其埋葬
...Alexander the Great studied with
亚历山大大帝奉伟大的哲学家
a great philosopher, Aristoteles.
亚里斯多德为师
He taught him all the Psalms.
教导他圣经中所有诗文
All the worthy men wondered at how fast he learned.
那些大人物都在想他能学多快
What, Carfin, do you feel the noose tightening?
怎么了 绳子太紧吗
He'll kill me, master.
他要杀了我 大人
I beg of you like I beg the Holy Virgin,
我像乞求圣母办乞求你们
put a word in for me with the boyar!
在公爵面前替我说说好话吧
I swear I'll show him you couldn't help it.
我保证会告诉他你是身不由己
I've been a constable for many years, I have his ear.
我当警察好几年了 他会听我的
May the Lord give you health!
祝你长命百岁
Same to all of us.
你也一样
If he wants to harm you, I won't let him.
他要想伤害你 我肯定不会答应
Some whipping, that's all.
顶多就抽几鞭子
That's bad too.
那也很惨
Tis no pleasure, but it passes
估计是 但你得忍
All goes away,Like the rain in May.
一切都会过去 就像五月天的雨
What?
什么
Or he'll choke me to death
他也可能掐死我
with hot pepper smoke, fuck his black soul...
用烟燻 嘟囔着去他妈的黑乌鸦
If you put in a word, I won't ever do another bad deed.
要是你帮我开脱 我肯定不会再做坏事
And if you need something, I'll help you.
如果你有需要 我赴汤蹈火在所不惜
Our Carfin eats humble pie...
卡芬低声下气了…
But in the ass of the humble the Devil sits cross-legged...
但这背后魔鬼还在翘着二郎腿呢
My shot wounds are hurting...
我的枪伤很疼…
Stop pouting like a duck, they ain't but cat scratches...
别唧唧歪歪了 不就跟小猫抓一样
'Twas your own doing for hiding from us...
那就是你躲我们的代价
You have a good life nowadays.
现在你们过得可好了
Who?
谁
You Gypsies.
你们吉普赛人啊
In the olden days, the Voivod woke up and said:
从前王子起床后会说
"Today I feel like hunting crows!"
今天我想抓几个奴隶
And they got some slaves up a tree
然后绑三个在树上
and the Voivod shot arrows at them
对着他们射箭
'til he killed one.
直到射死一个
'Til he hunted down a crow...
直到他射倒一个奴隶
Could be. Woe is us...
或许这就是我们的悲哀…
Easy, little master.
轻点 小主人
So they see you've come on foot...
这样他们会看到你走来…
It hurts, I can't walk.
很痛 我走不动
Better lame and on foot than blind and in the saddle.
瘸腿走着 总比瞎眼骑马好
Easy, master, it hurts.
慢点 很疼啊
Constable, I have a word with you.
警察 我有话想跟你说
Speak!
你说
My horse was stolen.
我的马被偷了
Where'd you keep it?
你把马栓哪儿
Behind the house...
屋子后面
And what am I to do?
那我要怎么办
Help me get the thief. I'll thank you with something.
帮我抓贼 我会给你报酬
First see if it didn't stray.
先看我会不会迷路吧
Look for it everywhere.
像这样四处找
As the saying goes:
俗话说
I was looking for my mare
骑着驴
and I found I was astride it...
找驴
Crow, is the boyar home?
吉普赛佬 那是公爵家吗
He ain't, master.
他不是 大人
Where's Vasile?
瓦希里在哪
I'll go get him.
我去找他
Where'd you find the crow?
你在哪找到这奴隶的
None of your business.
不关你的事
Have you paid your impost?
你缴税了吗
I'll come and check.
我回来再检查
We don't have nothin'!
我们啥都没有
What will we send to Istanbul
我们要怎么寄东西回伊斯坦堡
and all the others we owe?!
还有还其他人债
Want the Ivans or the Turks
你是想让俄国人或土耳其人
to come kill us?
来杀我们吗
But the boyar pardoned us last year...
但公爵去年赦免我们了…
That was last year... Easter don't come every day.
那是去年…复活节又不天天是
Rabble...
暴民
Fuck your whore mother, Carfin!
操你妈逼 卡芬
Get away,or I'll bash your head in.
走开 否则我就打烂你的脑袋
Stupid lowlife!
真他妈傻逼
'Twas because of him the boyar gave us such torment here!
都是因为他 公爵才折磨我们
He'll cane him 'til the flesh comes off his back.
他肯定会把他打得皮开肉绽
Mind the servants, they're like the pest.
别理这些人 他们像害虫一样
Scat now, or I'll whip-fuck you!
走开 否则打死你
Stupid people...
真是蠢货
We'll go have a word with Lady Sultana.
我们想跟索塔娜小姐说几句话
She's in the tower.
她被关在塔里
- Guard Carfin!  - Sure I will.
- 看好卡芬  - 好的
Tell her I'm here!
告诉她我来了
They got you, Carfin!
他们抓到你了 卡芬
- Take the night pot, it's full.  - Faster, crow.
- 夜壶拿走 满了  - 快点 吉普赛佬
Why didn't you throw it through the cracks?
干嘛不倒到裂缝里
Bless you, merciful lady.
上帝保佑你 可怜的小姐
May God give you happiness for your infinite good deeds.
愿上帝因你的善行让你快乐
I kiss your hand like a son.
让我像儿子般亲吻你的手
This is Ionita, my boy and my helper.
这是欧尼塔 我的儿子兼助理
Thank you for letting us in.
谢谢你接见我们
I didn't, you barged in. What do you want?
是你们硬闯进来的 你们想干嘛
To tell you how my heart burns when I see you suffering.
来告诉你见你如此受苦我心急如焚
We've come to hand Carfin over to the boyar...
我们来把卡芬交给公爵…
How did you find him?
你怎么找得到他的
Me?
我吗
An old man knows what's in his bag...
老人知道自己袋子里装了什么
What bag?
什么袋子
Don't you know the tale?
你没听过那故事吗
An old man was beating his wife with a bag
一个老人用袋子打他老婆
and people wondered,
大家都在猜袋子里是啥
not knowing the bag was filled with rocks.
没人知道袋子里装了石头
Where was he?
他当时躲在哪儿
Working for a craftsman.
在替一个工匠做事
Listen, he says the fault was yours
他说错并不在他
and the boyar shouldn't torment him...
公爵不该惩罚他的…
I just want to complain to our Father Metropolitan,
我想去跟市长申诉
but my husband keeps me locked up.
但我丈夫把我囚禁于此
What for, kind lady?
出于什么原因 可怜的夫人
The beastly beatings I've suffered
那些我所承受的无尽折磨
from this enemy of mine.
都来自我的心魔
Heart of mine, don't cry so.
那是心魔啊 别哭
She cries all the time.
她老是哭
I see.
我懂了
I thought he'd kill me.
我以为他会杀了我
I'll make a complaint, curse his soul.
我要去申诉 诅咒他的灵魂
What can we do, sweet lady? That's the way of the world,
我们又能如何 世界就是这样运转的
the man has the right to punish his wife.
男人有权惩罚他的妻子
That's our law.
这就是我们的律法
Yes, since Noah's days.
自从诺亚时代就如此了
Adam himself kicked Eve in the stomach...
亚当还踢过夏娃的肚子
Oh, keep your mouth shut!
你给我闭嘴
In the new law, and even in Ipsilanti's codes,
新的律法里 即便是王子订的律法
man is asked to beat his wife, but with kindness.
男人依然被要求殴打妻子 但须得温柔
What kindness? He broke my back.
哪有温柔 他打断了我的背
And I'm no lowborn or slave...
我可不是低下阶层或奴隶…
As Basarab's book of law says:
巴司罗布的律法书说
"Women shall be less castigated than men,
女人该比男人少受惩罚
as they are dimmer of wit
因为她们不够聪明
and weaker before sin"...
面对罪恶显得软弱
I'm a dean's daughter, not a...
我可是司祭长的女儿 不是…
Did he beat you with a cane, or a sword...?
他用棍子还是剑打你
With his fists.
用拳头
Then there's nothing to do.
那这就没办法了
Had he used a cane, I'd have taken your complaint myself.
他要是拿棍子 我就帮你申诉
But you have no grounds.
但你没理由了
I'm here for the night pot.
我来拿尿壶了
Even the Metropolitan would say he was right.
说不定连市长也会挺他
Being guilty of adultery...
这是通奸罪啊…
I'm not guilty of anything.
我一点罪都没有
Tell me what happened.
告诉我发生了什么事
Carfin says it was you who lured him...
卡芬说是你勾引他…
I will not speak of that.
我不会谈这件事
Merciful lady, he has a soul, too.
慈悲的小姐 他也是个人啊
If the boyar beats him,
要是公爵无故打他
or kills him for nothing...
甚至要杀他
'Tis a great sin on your head...
你的良心怎么过得去
Fine.
好吧
Tell the boyar it's my fault as well,
告诉公爵这也是我的错
so he'll leave him be.
他会放他走的
Many thanks.
多谢
We'll just interrogate him and give him his fair share.
我们会审他 适当加以处罚
By our Christian law.
用我们天主教的律法
Don't be distressed, I'll tell the boyar
别担心了 我会告诉公爵的
to be more gentle with you.
请他善待你
Thank you, Carfin. But he's a bad man.
谢谢你 但他是个坏男人
He said he'd lock me up in the monastery.
他说他会把我关去修道院
He only seems mean, but he's got a heart of gold.
他只是刀子嘴豆腐心
We'll talk to him. We'll leave you with God.
我来跟他谈 让上帝与你同在
Stay with God, lady!
与上帝同在 小姐
Close that!
关上
Long live our bright lord!
大人万寿无疆
I have seven children, bright lord.
我有七个孩子 英明的大人
Look at him.
你看他
Aferim, Costandin!
干得好啊 警察
Please, a word with you.
可以跟你说几句吗
Take the hawk.
老鹰抓好
I was sure you wouldn't find him.
我以为你抓不到他呢
I wanted to send a posse.
本来想派个搜查队的
We swore we'd find him!
我们发过誓会找到他
To serve your lordship, we'd go through fire.
为了您赴汤蹈火在所不辞
Aferim, Costandin,
干得好 警察
may you live as long as the Coltea Tower.
愿你如柯尔坦钟塔般永世长存
He who serves his master with zilos is loved by God.
忠心服伺主子的人会获上帝爱戴
True, bright lord!
真的 大人英明
Where had he run off to?
他跑去哪儿了
Working as a craftsman's slave.
替一个工匠当奴隶
In our county?
没有出境吗
No. Ionita found him.
不是 欧尼塔找到他的
He shot him, too.
他也开枪射了他
Aferim, Ionita!
干得好 欧尼塔
Good day, bright lord!
你好 大人
Watch this hawk well.
看好老鹰
It's a gift for Medvedkin.
那是给曼德维金的礼物
Yes, bright lord.
是的 大人
They caught Carfin, bright lord!
他们抓到卡芬了
'Course!
我知道
Gather the crows, the servants and the lady.
把吉普赛人都召集起来 男仆女仆统统都叫过来
Herd all the crows here!
把奴隶都叫过来
Bless you, bright lord!
上帝保佑 大人
And the chibouk.
烟管给我
Bright lord, how should I put this...
大人 我该怎么好意思呢
Right...
好吧
As agreed. Here.
照之前所说的 拿去吧
Thank you!
谢谢您
We need a writ of receipt for our ruler.
我们得写张领据
Of course.
当然
Where's that feather?
笔在哪儿
- Isn't it there?  - It isn't.
- 不在桌上吗  - 不在
- Here it was.  - You again.
- 找到了  - 又来了
Bright lord, there's something else.
禀报大人 其实还有另一件事
Say it.
说吧
I know that this filthy maggot blotted your honour...
我知道那混蛋破坏了您的名声
But we've learned he's not the only one guilty.
但我们听说这不只是他的问题
He is, but Lady Sultana is more at fault.
他是有错 但索塔娜小姐也有错
She confessed it herself.
而她自己也承认了
None of your business.
这跟你无关
Cobbler, stick to your last!
管好你份内的事就好
Of course.
当然
But 'tis my duty, if I smell trickery...
但这是我责任 倘若我觉得有问题
Noble lord, whip him,
大人 打一顿消消气就好了
just don't kill him.
请别杀他
Are you seeking trouble?
你在找麻烦吗
Tired of being a lawkeeper here?
治安官当腻了是吧
No, bright lord.
不是的 大人
Well, then...
你想怎样
I was just thinking...
我只是在想…
Wax!
盖印
Take this!
拿去吧
God bless you.
上帝保佑您
Your ishlik, master!
您的帽子 大人
Sara, come with us!
莎拉 跟我们来
He's a smart, hardworking slave...
他是个聪明努力的奴隶
- Who?  - Carfin.
- 谁  - 卡芬
Bring that dagger!
那把刀带着
How about we write Mahmud over in Istanbul?
我们写信去伊斯坦堡给曼汉姆如何
- Who?  - We.
- 谁  - 我们啊
To ask him to award Carfin the Nishan Iftikhar order,
请他颁个徽章给卡芬
since he's such a good Gypsy.
因为他是这么好的吉普赛人
Or the Russians,to give him the Saint Vladimir?
或者请俄国人封他当圣者
Psihi-mu, a word with you,if I may.
可以跟你说句话吗
What words could you have with me?
你想跟我说什么
I have thoughts that put me in great turmoil...
总觉得这让我心乱如麻
Iordache, please!
拜托啦
Shedding many a bitter tear For her fun of yester year.
得为她过去的流些眼泪了
Where's that Vasile?
瓦希里在哪儿
He went to fetch Lady Sultana.
他去请索塔娜小姐了
Tell him to hurry!
告诉他我饿了
Forgive him, master!
原谅他吧
Take pity!
请可怜他
What, they forgot the water when they christened you?
搞什么 你受洗时他们忘了带水吧
He'll be fine.
他会没事的
Enough whining!
别在哀嚎了
May your lady and your bright children live long and happy!
愿您全家永远快乐
Are you pleased, agapi-mu, for making me the town's laughingstock?
你高兴了吧 让我成为城里的笑柄
Me, your honourable spouse?
我还是你尊贵的丈夫
And with a Gypsy, too?!
还有那个吉普赛人
Everyone laughs at me like I'm an idiot.
大家都把我当白痴嘲笑
Even the chickens laugh at me. Even toddlers.
连鸡都在笑我 小孩子也是
Get him out of the stocks!
把他抓住
Vasile! Grab his hands!
瓦希里 抓住他的手
Carfin's, you idiot!
卡芬 你这白痴
Get him!
抓住他
Oh, Carfin!
卡芬
Such a snake I raised by my manor...
养虎为患
Such a venomous viper...
引狼入室
Let him be, it wasn't his fault!
放了他吧 这不是他的错
You soiled my life, you crow!
你糟蹋了我的一生 吉普赛佬
Forgive me, master, 'tain't my fault!
原谅我 不是我的错
I treated you well, like all my slaves.
跟其他奴隶一样 我也待你不薄
I gave you food, I gave you clothing,
给你吃 给你穿
I didn't beat you... And you...
不打不骂 而你却…
Venomous asp!
你良心被狗吃了
It was her fault,not mine!
是她的错 不是我
Don't kill him!
别杀他
Help, kind people, he'll kill me!
救命啊 他要杀我
Constable, help me!
警察 救我
Noble lord, better let him get his punishment from the ruler,
大人 最好让他依照规定
by the law...
遵照律法接受惩罚…
You shut up!
你闭嘴
Out of my sight, worm!
滚远一点
Vasile! Raise his legs!
瓦希里 把他的腿举起来
Give me the dagger!
刀子给我
Raise his cock, too!
掏出他的老二来
Hold him!
抓住他
Bright lord, try with this.
大人 用这个
That'll teach him!
让我们教教他
Let it be a lesson to you all.
给你们都上上一课
If you think of doing such things here.
要是想在这儿干这档事
I'll find out.
我会发现的
Cut his cock too, master!
把他老二切掉 大人
Here, kera-mu, eat his bollocks
拿去 吃了他卵蛋
since you were so fond of loving...
既然你这么爱…
Walk him around town,
带他去游街示众
for all to see he's lost his bollocks,
让所有人看到他被阉了
then bring him back, I have more to discuss with him.
然后带他回来 我要跟他谈谈
Then take his wife to the fair and trade her for another,
然后带他老婆去市集 换另一个回来
I will not see her here again.
我永远不要再见到她
Understood, bright lord.
明白 大人
Only the law doesn't allow to break apart a clan of slaves...
但法律规定不准拆散奴隶家庭
That's your job!
那是你的事
Bribe someone if you must.
有需要就去打点
Let's go back home, son.
我们回家吧 儿子
Stultus numerus infinitus...
愚昧真的是没有下限
Come on, fuck it, don't be a rag.
离开这 别看笑话了
Be a man, not flesh with eyes!
男儿有泪不轻弹
I'm fine, father.
我没啥 父亲
He ain't your fuckin' brother.
他又不是你兄弟
God even looks after worms
上帝连蠕虫都眷顾
and we can't look after each other...
我们却无法照顾彼此…
This world will stay as it is,
世界会继续如此
you can't change it, try as you might.
你改变不了什么 你只能尽力而为
We live as we can, not as we want.
我们有力存活 无力为所欲为
But you'll be fine, my boy.
但你没事的 儿子
I'll get you into the army,
我会让你进军队
you'll be a real man.
你会成为真爷们
You'll live through a war or two, you'll make officer,
你会经历一两场战争成为军官
mark my words.
记住我的话
See?
懂了吗
Life will be better
人生终将更美好
and we'll have a chance to rest.
到时我们就有机会稍作休息
Some narrative situations and pieces of dialogue
本片部分叙事情境与对话
have been taken from historical documents
取材自罗马尼亚历史资料